The Volcano: Rescue from Whakaari is a documentary,
drama film directed by Rory Kennedy.
A close examination of the Whakaari / White Island volcanic eruption of 2019 in which 22 lives were lost, the film viscerally recounts a day when ordinary people were
called upon to do extraordinary things, placing this tragic event within the larger context of nature, resilience, and the power of our shared humanity.
On 9 December 2019, Whakaari / White Island, an active stratovolcano island in New
Zealand's northeastern Bay of Plenty region, explosively erupted.
The island was a popular tourist destination, known for its volcanic
activity, and 47 people were on the island at the time.
Twenty-two people died, either in the explosion or from injuries sustained,
including two whose bodies were never found, later declared dead.
The remaining 25 people suffered injuries, with the
majority needing intensive care for severe burns.
Continuing seismic and volcanic activity, together with heavy rainfall, low visibility and the
presence of toxic gases, hampered recovery efforts over the week following the incident.
Experts identified the event as a phreatic eruption: a release of steam and volcanic
gases that caused an explosion, launching rock and ash into the air.
Following the eruption, investigations resulted in WorkSafe New Zealand charging the owners of the island and multiple tour operators as well as
government and scientific agencies under the Health and Safety at Work Act 2015 for failing to ensure the health and safety of workers and others.
As of July 2023, the charges against two government agencies have been dismissed or dropped
and five tour operators have pleaded guilty to health and safety charges.
The trial of six remaining defendants (three individual owners of the island
and three tour operating companies) commenced on 11 July 2023.
In early September 2023, Judge Evangelos Thomas dismissed the individual charges against the island's owners Peter,
Andrew, and James Buttle but upheld the charges against their company Whakaari Management Limited (WML).
On 12 September, Thomas dismissed the charges against co-defendants Tauranga Tourism
Services (TTSL) and ID Tours, reducing the number of defendants to one.
On 31 October, WML was convicted of one health and
safety charge relating to the eruption.
On 1 March 2024, Judge Thomas imposed a total of NZ$10.21 million in reparations and NZ$2 million in fines on the six defendants
Whakaari Management Limited, White Island Tours, Volcanic Air Safaris, Kahu Limited, Aerius, and GNS Science.
On 28 February 2025, Justice Simon Moore overturned
Whakaari Management Limited's conviction.
The film explores themes of natural disaster, new zealand,
rescue mission, interview, rescue team.
The tone is emotional.